<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>temperancee&#39;s hovel</title>
    <link>/</link>
    <description>temperancee&#39;s hovel</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-gb</language>
    
      

      
    

    
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 18 Jun 2025 19:46:13 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    
    <atom:link href="/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>About</title>
      <link>/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Jun 2025 19:46:13 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/about/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;My name is Myles, but I&amp;rsquo;m floating temperancee as my latest (and greatest) screen name.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m a third year mathematics student who spends his time building robots and programming things (like robots, but not &lt;em&gt;just&lt;/em&gt; robots).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On this website you can expect to find documentation of my projects, as well as some more general blog posts relating to programming, robotics, Vim, Linux, maths, and whatever else.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Enjoy your stay.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Welcome</title>
      <link>/home/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Jun 2025 19:34:41 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/home/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;nothing&#34; &gt;
&lt;div&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#nothing&#34;&gt;
        ##
    &lt;/a&gt;
    Nothing
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;what&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The classic first blog post, a note on this website</title>
      <link>/blog/this_website/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Jun 2025 20:38:56 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/this_website/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A little spiel on how and why I made this website.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;a-website-how&#34; &gt;
&lt;div&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#a-website-how&#34;&gt;
        ##
    &lt;/a&gt;
    A website! How?
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With ease.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve made a personal website before actually. I crafted it out of raw html and css, no frameworks, or whatever, just as Tim Berners-Lee intended.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$ \frac{2}{3} $$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This time around I wanted things to&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Just be plain easier to code, so I actually &lt;em&gt;use&lt;/em&gt; the damn thing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Feel a bit more&amp;hellip; put together&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I made this website using Hugo, the docs for which leave a &lt;em&gt;little&lt;/em&gt; to be desired in terms of a tutorial - it&amp;rsquo;s sort of like &amp;ldquo;so here&amp;rsquo;s how to install themes and make content - right! That&amp;rsquo;s all! Have fun wandering round the other doc pages slowly piecing everything else together!&amp;rdquo;. Whatever. I got it working easily enough.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;del&gt;Future me can pick this up, I might edit the CSS, which would certainly change the content of this article&lt;/del&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;a-website-eyes-why&#34; &gt;
&lt;div&gt;
    &lt;a href=&#34;#a-website-eyes-why&#34;&gt;
        ##
    &lt;/a&gt;
    A website &amp;#x1f440;!? Why?
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I needed a place to document my projects. I plan to make YouTube videos on them too, but videos are effort. Writing little posts is much easier (plus it acts as a sort of draft for the video script - two turds with one bone!).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also wanted a place to share some writings. Mini-essays of sorts. I realised I should write more - get the thoughts out there - &lt;em&gt;distill things&lt;/em&gt;. I&amp;rsquo;ve got a post coming up about teaching fractions, decimals, and division of them to children, motivated by my struggle trying to teach said topics to my little cousin.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And finally, like the home page &lt;del&gt;says&lt;/del&gt; (will say):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;I ask, &amp;lsquo;cause I&amp;rsquo;m not sure, do anybody make real shit anymore?&amp;rdquo; - K. West, &lt;em&gt;Stronger&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Social media just ain&amp;rsquo;t got the &lt;strong&gt;vibe&lt;/strong&gt;. Same profile layout, same black background (because you&amp;rsquo;re not &lt;em&gt;seriously&lt;/em&gt; using Instagram in light mode are you?) - it&amp;rsquo;s a damn shame. That&amp;rsquo;s part of the reason I whacked this thing on &lt;a href=&#34;https://neocities.org/browse&#34;&gt;Neocities&lt;/a&gt; (also because it&amp;rsquo;s free): you see some real creativity from some real deranged people on there - &lt;em&gt;just as Tim Berners-Lee intended&lt;/em&gt;. Webpages should contain knowledge and vibes, not slop.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
