<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Blogs on temperancee&#39;s hovel</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/blog/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Blogs on temperancee&#39;s hovel</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-gb</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 08 Jul 2025 22:23:51 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/blog/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Micropython X Neovim</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/blog/micropython_x_neovim/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Jul 2025 22:23:51 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/blog/micropython_x_neovim/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;As you may know, my editor of choice is Neovim, the finest editor in the game. This post teaches you how to get a barebones environment setup for working on Micropython projects with Neovim. This won&amp;rsquo;t cover setting up a proper Neovim environment, just how your can take an already well-developed environment and tailor it for Micropython development.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h1 id=&#34;reader-prerequistes&#34;&gt;Reader prerequistes&lt;/h1&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;A Neovim setup&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Understanding of LSPs in Neovim&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Understanding of Python virtual environments&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Basic familiarity with your shell (since this is a Neovim article, you probably know more than enough)&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h1 id=&#34;neovim-lsp&#34;&gt;Neovim LSP&lt;/h1&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;There are many LSPs for Python, some of which you can read about by opening Neovim and running &amp;ldquo;:h lspconfig-all&amp;rdquo;, to see the detailed list of all the LSPs for Neovim (note you need the &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/neovim/nvim-lspconfig&#34;&gt;lspconfig plugin&lt;/a&gt; to see this).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The classic first blog post, a note on this website</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/blog/this_website/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Jun 2025 20:38:56 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/blog/this_website/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A little spiel on how and why I made this website.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h1 id=&#34;a-website-how&#34;&gt;A website! How?&lt;/h1&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;With ease.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve made a personal website before actually. I crafted it out of raw html and css, no frameworks, or whatever, just as Tim Berners-Lee intended.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;$$ \frac{2}{3} $$&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This time around I wanted things to&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Just be plain easier to code, so I actually &lt;em&gt;use&lt;/em&gt; the damn thing&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Feel a bit more&amp;hellip; put together&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;So I made this website using Hugo, the docs for which leave a &lt;em&gt;little&lt;/em&gt; to be desired in terms of a tutorial - it&amp;rsquo;s sort of like &amp;ldquo;so here&amp;rsquo;s how to install themes and make content - right! That&amp;rsquo;s all! Have fun wandering round the other doc pages slowly piecing everything else together!&amp;rdquo;. Whatever. I got it working easily enough.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
